Finding Aid for Helen Hornbeck Tanner papers, 1930s-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- U.S. v. Michigan (case of Indian claims against the state of Michigan on matters of fishing rights)
  - Other documents 1975-1979
    - Plaintiff-intervenors' (Bay Mills Indian Community) first set of interrogatories June 2, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Second motion of the state-defendants for partial summary judgment May 2, 1977 (Box 10)
    - Plaintiff's and plaintiff-intervenors' memorandum of points and authorities in opposition of the state's second motion for partial summary judgment June 17, 1977 (Box 10)
    - Joint proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law of the United States of America, Bay Mills Indian Community and the Sault Ste. Marie Tribe of Chippewa Indians January 5, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Declaratory judgment and decree May 7, 1979 with Miscellaneous disclosure, May 7, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Plaintiff's exhibits (exhibits 1-7, 15-16, and 125-129 are omitted), 3 volumes (Box 10)
  - Native American Rights Fund documents
    - Notes on deposition of Arthur L. LeBlanc (Box 10)
    - Notes on deposition of Joseph K. Lumsden (Box 10)
    - Notes on deposition of Philip P. Mason (Box 10)
    - Notes on deposition of Helen Hornbeck Tanner (Box 10)
    - Notes on report of Helen Hornbeck Tanner (Box 10)
    - Copies of decisions on U.S. v. Michigan
      - November 15, 1978 (Box 10)
      - May 8, 1979 (Box 10)
      - May 9, 1980 (Box 10)
      - May 28, 1980, August 18, 1981, March 19, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Reports and other materials
    - Report (Helen Hornbeck Tanner) April 1974 (Box 11)
    - Supplementary Report (Helen Hornbeck Tanner) August 1976 (Box 11)
    - Report United States of America v. State of Michigan (Charles E. Cleland) June 1976 (Box 11)
    - Clippings 1978-1980 (Box 11)
    - Notes taken on proceedings testimony 1978 (Box 11)
    - Working file 1973-1979, 1 expandable folder (Box 11)
- Other Litigation
  The Other Litigation series documents Tanner's historical research and contribution as expert witness to such cases as United States and Saginaw Chippewa Tribe v. Michigan (1992) and the Turtle River Casino gambling case, Grand Traverse Band of Ottawa and Chippewa Indians v. United States Attorney for the Western District of Michigan and the State of Michigan.
  - Potawatomi entity combined case 1972 (Citizen Band of Potawatomi Indians of Oklahoma; Pottawatomie Tribe of Indians; Hannahville Indian Community, et al. v. United States of America
    - Court documents and research materials (multiple folders) (Box 11)
  - Sioux Nation et al, The Yankton Sioux Tribe v. the United States (Box 12)
    - Expert witness file 1976-1979, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - United States and Saginaw Chippewa Tribe v. Michigan 1992
    - Report of the Nineteenth Century History of the Saginaw, Black River and Swan Creek Chippewa (Charles E. Cleland) October 16, 1992 (Box 12)
    - List of Documents Collected for the Saginaw Chippewa Indian Tribe (submitted by Charles E. Cleland) June 5, 1992 (Box 12)
    - Isabella Saginaw documents (list of sources, list of abbreviations, bibliography) generated by Dr. Clifton and submitted to the Court (Box 12)
    - Calendar of Research for the Saginaw Chippewa 1992 (Box 12)
      (2 drafts)
    - Report: "An Overview of Federal Relations with the Saginaw, Swan Creek, and Black River Bands of Chippewa of the Isabella Indian Reservation, Michigan: 1910-1934" (prepared by Alan S. Newell) October 16, 1992 (Box 12)
    - Saginaw Chippewa Indian Tribe of Michigan (photocopied documents from the National Archives) 1937 (Box 12)
    - Notes on depositions (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1992 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous documents 1991-1992 (Box 12)
  - Sisseton-Wahpeton Sioux Tribes v. US 1996
    - File of findings with footnotes (Box 12)
  - Minnesota v. Mille Lac Band
    - Memoranda and other court materials 1997-1998 (Box 12)
    - US Supreme Court decision 1999 (Box 12)
  - Saginaw Chippewa Indian Tribe of Michigan v. Jennifer M. Granholm, et al. 2007
    - Response to Defendants' Expert Reports (Box 12)
    - Plaintiff's Expert Reports (Box 12)
  - United States and Bay Mills Indian Community Sault Ste. Marie Tribe of Chippewa Indians, et al. v. State of Michigan, et al.
    - Frederick Hoxie expert witness report and related 2004-2005 (Box 12)
    - Consent decrees 2007 (Box 12)
  - Grand Traverse Band of Ottawa and Chippewa Indians v. United States Attorney for the Western District of Michigan and the State of Michigan (Turtle Creek Casino gambling case)
    - Court documents and related 1998-1999 (multiple folders) (Box 13)
  - Caddo Tribe of Oklahoma, et al. v. United States of America (Indian Claims Commission Docket 226)
    - Correspondence and legal papers 1970-1973, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - "The Territory of the Caddo Tribe of Oklahoma" Plaintiff's exhibit T-216 prepared by HHT (Box 14)
  - Ohio Land Claim of the Ottawa Tribe of Oklahoma for North Bass Island Ottawa County, Ohio
    - Documentation for claim, correspondence, and related material 2005-2007, 6 folders (Box 14)
- Printed material
  The Printed material series includes professional archaeological journals, periodical journals specializing in Native American history, and various newspapers and newsletters.
  - Professional archaeological journals, periodical journals specializing in Native American history, etc.; include issues of Caddoan Archaeology, and Le Journal among other publications (Box 14)
Related Materials
The Bentley Historical Library holds a collection of maps donated by Tanner, relating to her work as an expert witness in cases before the Indian Claims Commission. This collection is part of the library's map collection (M 4112 .L7E1 1810 T3) and is fully described in MIRLYN, the U-M online catalog.
The Newberry Library holds a collection of Tanner's papers. The collection included personal and professional correspondence, research notes, research notebooks, card files, Potawatomi (1997) and Caddo court case materials, and research files and data for maps in Settling of North America (1995).